So we spoke about perception. So say now
things that you perceive directly
looking at me and everything else
peripherally with the corner of your eye
even even tactile whatever perceptions
as a whole what is a common
characteristic to all of that what would
be a common thread if you look at what
you're feeling like on your legs what
you're seeing with your eyes what would
be the common thing to those
my body being here me being conscious
okay yeah but the characteristic
characteristic the the property
the the property
How would you describe
like a certain unifying characteristic
for all of it?
I'm conscious of the experience of
whatever seen, heard, felt.
So you are conscious of the experience.
How can you differentiate your
consciousness from the experience you're
conscious of?
Is that possible?
I I would say no.
Exactly. Yeah. So, so like, oh, I'm
conscious. That's not really accurate,
isn't it? That's that's like a um a
common attitude, but it's not really a
representative attitude. So, it's you're
only conscious or you can only even
think I am conscious of this because
it's there. So, I'm asking you what are
the properties of things that are there.
What is what how would you describe it
in your own words? There's no right or
wrong answer. As I said before,
things a characteristic of them being there or
a characteristic of them being there or
how.
Yeah. Okay. So, let's let's be more
specific. So, you see his body, you see
that stone, you see this cave, you see
the dog.
Mhm. So, you might have different attitude
So, you might have different attitude
towards it. You might like this, dislike
that. But I'm talking about things that
you just perceive.
Did you have a say in them? Do you have
a say in how the She got excited. Do you
have a say in how the cave is being
perceived? No.
No.
Do you have a say in how your eyes work?
No. I wouldn't.
Do you have a say on how your legs are
feeling the ground and whatever you're
leaning on? Do you have a say in
anything tactile you're exposed to?
So, see that's that's the unifying
characteristic to all of it.
You're subjected to it. You have no
control over it within things. you're
subjected to
that you perceive on all sorts of
levels. By the way, even your thoughts.
Do you have a say in how your thoughts
appear? I don't. Impossible. Like it's actually
I don't. Impossible. Like it's actually
even inconceivable to to imagine how it
would be if I were to have a say. You
can't you can't even conceive that. Yet
by not thinking about how impossible is
to actually entertain the notion of
ownership of these things, that's how
you entertain the ownership.
You can respond to thoughts, but that's
always just something that's already
there in as much you respond to perceptions,
in as much you respond to perceptions,
tactile, visual, uh, audible, whatever.
The point is, you can only respond to
what pressures you.
But I was asking you what is the common
thread to all things and that's it. They
pressure you.
You have no say in there arising. Which
means you're subjected to perception.
That's when I asked you earlier on, can
you stop perceiving? You can close your
eyes, but you're perceiving the inside
of your eyes.
Can you stop thinking? Can you stop
having tactile sensations for as long as
the body is there? Impossible.
Yet somehow, despite all that
overwhelming proof and and and and and
like confirmation that you're not in
control, people's minds keep maintaining
the notion that you are in control of
things you see, hear, smell, taste, and
touch, and think.
No, you're only in control in regard to
how you choose to act.
Hence, karma and all the beings are
owners of their action and responsible
for the results of it. That is your
respon like you're not responsible for
how things are subjected on you. But how
you choose to act on account of it,
that's not in perception.
That's not in the pressure. That's in
you choosing to act out of that
pressure. So that's why you can never ever
So that's why you can never ever
possibly escape responsibility for your
choice. Doesn't matter the circumstances
by the way. Oh, you know, I had to kill
him because he was a threat or
something. No, you killed him because
you chose to do so.
There is no such thing as I had to do
this as opposed to I didn't have to do the
as opposed to I didn't have to do the
opposite. That's why you cannot step
outside of that responsibility by
adhering to like a an external set of
values and so on. External set of values
can help you gain the right perspective
on your responsibility but it's still on
you. That's why even sila and virtue is
is a feta to begin with. The first feta
silas fatter of virtue sense of duty
the feder in the sense that
um you see
you're not putting them in the right
order. You're seeing them as
well, you're not putting your
responsibility first. You're not seeing
that correctly. Which again, first you
need to restrain acts of
irresponsibility such as sensuality, ill
will, cheating, lying, stealing and so
on. So you need to keep the precepts.
You don't know why. You don't see
directly why. You have some notion. But
if you do it, you are restraining your
irresponsible actions. Actions that are
based on avoiding responsibility.
And that's how you get to discern the
responsibility in regard to it.
But the point is that it all starts by
recognizing that things you're subjected
to, you are subjected to have no saying
them. And that's including your own
perception
when they they're describing you know
like perceiving the solidity.
So you're determining through your
thoughts. I mean, it's all given to you.
The body's there. You're subjected to it
and you're supposed to see how you're
subjected to that.
You're not you're not supposed to see
anything. You're supposed to stop craving in
You're supposed to stop craving in
regard to how you feel.
That's it. So if on account of that
towards that goal you get to understand
the nature of solidity which not it's
nothing other than basically
understanding something more primordial
than your sense of self something more
fundamental something that's not cannot
be your sense of self yet your sense of
self depends upon it. That's the point.
Not like I must follow this perception
and figure out that perception. It's all
for the sake of preventing you from
craving towards how you feel. You can't
choose to not crave because it's going
to be rooted in craving. But if you set
up the order rightly, you can simply
make yourself unable to crave.
And so that that can be done by
developing certain perceptions because
there are certain perceptions that
reveal that exactly certain perceptions
that will be um resulting in the right
order. Yeah. Yeah.
More accurately.
Which is why
but again unless you have a notion of
what the right order is there is no
right perception for you.
Yeah yeah yeah.
If you start in the wrong order but know
that there is the right order can you
apply the perception to reach the right
order. You have to keep trying. That's the
You have to keep trying. That's the
point. Yeah.
But in order to do it accurately Yeah. Yeah.
in order to do it accurately Yeah. Yeah.
With a degree of faith. Yeah. In order
to do it accurately you must not forget
that it is the wrong order. you're going
through. So don't like lose the context that
So don't like lose the context that
you're actually seeking the right order
recognition of it which is not at the
end of certain set of perceptions and so
on
or I do this or I do that. It's right
there with you and you're not seeing it
because it's too close to your point of
view and you're not used to seeing
things so close. And by close I mean
right there but not directly visible.
It's like learning to see things without
looking at them. See, I'm looking at
you, but corners of my peripheral
vision, I'm seeing other things. But I'm
usually you don't think about things
that are peripheral. You think about
what you attend to.
So, you want to learn how to start
discerning peripheral without needing to
move my face and look at the peripheral
because that's not peripheral.
Mhm. Now that's which was peripheral is now
Now that's which was peripheral is now
directly visible actual for me. Now
you're peripheral.
The point is understanding the nature of
peripheral not what's in peripheral.
What perception is in peripheral.
You want to understand the nature of
seeing things without needing to look at
them. That's like the the how did we refer to
That's like the the how did we refer to
the internal eye so to speak. So seeing
So seeing
seeing and what's implied by that seeing
that I'm seeing something
but simultaneously there is peripheral
to see well
it is but again what what what are you
seeing whatever you're seeing that is
peripheral to that thing that you're
attending to that's already where your
body is. It's on the level of the
peripheral. So understanding the
framework of peripheral
without needing to look at it. Same
works for the thoughts by the way.
There's a thought present but then
there's all these other peripheral
context to it. So that's how you get to
understand when we spoke before like
motivation intentions behind your
actions because they're always
peripheral reasons why you're doing such
and such thing is not in you attending
to that thing visibly.
You attend to that thing visibly and
actually and tactally because there is
the intention to do so which is
peripheral to it which is determining
your set of actions.
But generally the direction is going to
be
not so much
the peripheral is implied by what I
attend to as if it's kind of secondary
to it. It's actually the other way
around that everything that I'm doing
now is undermined by something
is undermined by something
that should be hopefully the
realization. Now it's oh it's because I look at this
Now it's oh it's because I look at this
all of this is peripheral but then the
time comes when you get used to that you
realize no all of this was peripheral
until I looked at that which means
everything else has stayed a peripheral
which means peripheral is more
fundamental than whatever you choose to
and the only reason you could look at it
is because it was given as an option
within the peripheral. If this thing was
not there on the level of everything
else that's peripheral there, I couldn't
have singled it out.
So that's when you realize the
peripheral is actually more fundamental
than the actual.
And you can do that on the level of
visual as well if you need an aid so to
speak. So if you're looking at the dog
now and oh, I must think about
peripheral. Can you learn how to see
peripheral while you're looking at the
dog without stopping to think about the
dog? As in I become glazed. I don't forget
As in I become glazed. I don't forget
what I'm actually seeing and I'm
thinking about everything else around
me. No, now that became actual for you.
So no, I am looking at the dog for
whatever reason and there is all this
peripheral around me and it's not the
point to figure it out. The point is to
learn how to be um how to not completely
ignore it the peripheral without need
without giving to the need of attending
it directly.
It's like a
So what's the overall feeling you have
now while we speak? Pleasant, unpleasant
or neutral?
Neutral. Neutral. That's already peripheral to
Neutral. That's already peripheral to
any action you're doing, any situation
you're involved with. It's there
enduring. If it weren't there, you
couldn't have given me the answer. You
wouldn't even my question would not have
been intelligible to you. Huh? But you
understood it.
Which means that feeling is there and
it's still there enduring. Time is
passing. It's the same feeling enduring
in the course of time.
The same peripheral framework.
sort of like um
driving a car, you need you can't be
putting your line of vision like this
way, that way like all the time. You
need to have
a basic
sense of the space
and you mustn't
take your eyes away from the road.
You can't even afford to attend to the
peripheral. Yeah. Otherwise you could crash someone.
Yeah. Otherwise you could crash someone.
Exactly. Yeah. So the point is then to
learn how to discern what you're feeling
without needing to because you can't
look at what you're feeling. You can't
perceive your feeling. So what are you
attending to? You can't even attend to
it in that sense.
So that's why the Buddha said his
teaching is for the one who knows how to
feel as in who knows how to feel as in
knows what the feeling is in itself
and he feels it without the need to
attend to it and start to perceive it
because usually that's the idea oh I get
this or let me look at it to get the
clarity in regard to no that if you go
to the particular way you can attend
that's not where the clarity is clarity
of things it's in its nature and that
itself is peripheral or
is a suit to where
the Buddhist says the um
there's nothing more that needs to be
done by someone who's fully understood
feeling. Exactly. It's the ultimate context is to
Exactly. It's the ultimate context is to
understand what feeling is. Yeah, that's
it. Thorough understanding of the of the
peripheral context of the feeling or
simply thorough understanding of feeling
because it's always peripheral uh means
absolute removal for any slightest basis
for craving to be there. No craving
there is no more work for you to do.
And by the way, it's not about some
future feeling or something later on.
It's about the current feeling you have
of the neutral kind.
That is the point.
So yes, stay in the present without
attending to the present, but discern it
instead because you can't attend to your
because you can't attend to your
feeling. It's not an object there that
you can look at.
Hence, feeling feels perception
perceives. As the Buddha said, not
perceiving feels and feeling perceives.
Yeah. That would be it would be like
thinking it would be like trying to perceive
it would be like trying to perceive
feeling, but what I'm really just
perceiving is my thought.
Exactly. in regard
but you have a view that you are
perceiving the feeling
and that's why you'll never then find
make effort to feel what the real
feeling is and that's why you will never
make the effort to remove the basis for
credit you'll be unable to
but if you learn how to feel as in not
to try and perceive it but realize it
doesn't matter what you perceive it
cannot be felt feeling can be felt
simultaneously peripheral to your
perception
then you're becoming much more familiar
will be the necessary basis for craving
and craving in order to be there
requires the ignorance of the necessary
basis for craving. Thus, understanding
feeling removes craving. Non-under
understanding feeling maintains craving.
There is nothing else in between you
need to do.
So, understand the peripheral, the
background of your mind. Now while we
speak of that neutral feeling,
understand its characteristics, its
properties, its nature
and you get to understand the right
context and you get to reestablish the
right order.
Did you have a say in that feeling being
manifested or you just found it?
Just found it.
But can you not feel it? Can you not
feel any pressure of it?
There is pressure.
It has to. It has to always. So you just
found it yet you're subjected to it. Is
it then right to say that that feeling
is yours in your control? Obeys your
will. Is it even right to say that that
Is it even right to say that that
feeling knows about you? How can it even
know about you?
You don't exist for that. Yet here you
are living your whole life revolving on
account of how you feel.
And it's always been like that and
always will be like that unless the mind
develops itself out of it. Yet that
feeling doesn't even know who you are.
You don't exist for it literally. You
cannot exist for it. In the same sense
upana cannot exist for the five
aggregates not knowing that upan is
there in regard to them as the Buddha
said.
So understand that indifference of
whatever feeling is there doesn't matter
if it's pleasant unpleasant or neutral
indifference to you to your life and
then you will also understand
what it means or rather what what what
it was before when you were subjected to
it and when you needed to act out of
that pressure. Pressure for pleasure,
pressure for getting rid of pain. It's
only done so you only act out of it
because you still kind of don't
understand that that pain and pleasure
are indifferent and your actions are
equally insignificant to it. Your
actions cannot make a difference to the
fact that you're subjected to feelings.
Your actions are only secondary result
your response
your kind of desperate response towards
being subjected to feelings. If your
actions would make a difference to it,
well, you would have already been free
from being subjected to feelings because
you acted every possible way in this
life. You said yes, you said no, you
said neither. You abstain, you you were
unclear. All of those movements
the pressure was there. Made no
difference to it. So you want to
understand that pressure doesn't care
about your movements. Cannot doesn't
even know about it. So then you can
restrain the movements that would be uh
perpetuating need to move which is
movement of desire, greed, aversion,
anger, distraction, delusion,
carelessness. And again that's what Buddha said. You
And again that's what Buddha said. You
can't like stop the pressure. You can't
stop thoughts. You can't stop the
perception. But you can stop acting unh
wholesomely out of it
because you understand that that it's
indifference in regard.
You understand the nature of it. You
understand that that you cannot partake
in it. You cannot command it. You cannot
will it. You cannot control it. Thus,
any attempt at controlling it becomes
redundant. You're only attempting to
control it because you still have an
implicit view that you can in some
manner. And for as long as you don't remove that
And for as long as you don't remove that
view, you are not removing desire and
lust and anger.
So any attempt to control that feeling
or get rid of that feeling becomes
meaningless. Exactly. Utterly meaningless.
Exactly. Utterly meaningless.
Lust becomes utterly meaningless. anger.
Acting out of anger becomes
inconceivable. Yeah.
Yeah.
Not because you need to go through the
psychological movement. Oh, anger is
bad. Anger is not good. No, it's just
inconceivable to do so.
There's no uh need for restraint. Like
it just it just doesn't make any sense
anymore.
She's calm down.
Yeah, she still has that wild side to her.
she still has that wild side to her.
Well, she's been with us what three
weeks, but she's quite good, quick learner.
So that's what mean like even when you
read the sutras and all these
perceptions of this and infinite space,
one step at a time. As the Buddha said
even in terms of like Janna if you oh a
mind wants to enter second Janna hasn't
even established itself become familiar
with the first one you'll enter naida
you'll establish a mind upon ne
because it's the same principle that's
just been refined further and further so
if you haven't even established the
basis of that principle how can you
refine it when you have nothing to
refine so always come back to either present
so always come back to either present
situation of the body body posture
whichever way it's enduring perceptions
you're subject to feeling that's
enduring peripheral. That is the
framework. And by the way, you don't
need to understand more than that.
Understand the body being present there
on its own indifferent
um ignorant of you doesn't even know
about your existence. Understand that to
the extent necessary for removal of all
the lust, a diversion, delusion and
you'll be an arant
and no need to think about perceptions
of infinite space and
and so on
cuz you already covered it.
does speak of I guess I mean in regard
to that you're saying that's just the
baseline of what you need to understand
to be liberated free from suffering
and but they were a hunts that had
extended knowledge in regard to
extended knowledge but doesn't matter
how extended it was it was within the
thing you understood
it wasn't like an extra an addendum or
something like
But some people like sort of conflate
that like oh ours had genres.
Yeah. They conflate with all these
diversity of knowledge and all these
different things you get to figure out.
But no it's just different aspects more
no it's just different aspects more
defined aspects within the same frame of
the same thing which is suffering and
freedom from craving in regard to it.
That's why the Buddha was able to
distinguish between different types of
arahhat like um
like um
yeah they're all Araanss.
Yeah. But you got the body witness they
aren't. Yeah. Like the
but it's all up on with wisdom.
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah.
The ones who were liberated both ways.
They weren't
just different whether whether they'd
gone through all these
establishments of mind.